Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going
to be learning about stoichiometry.
Now with this concept, this is something
that all chemistry students eventually
will have to learn, which is essentially
taking all of the different skills
that you've been learning throughout
the semester and tying them together
and relating them through the chemical
formula or through relationships that
you've learned about in dimensional
analysis or through equations and swap
drops, all these different methods.
Now, whenever you see this
pronunciation, pronunciation here,
Stoy-key-aa-muh-tree Stoichiometry, right?
So saying that out loud to yourself
because most likely there's going to
be you and about five other classmates
that will struggle with pronouncing
this, but it's not that scary.
It's not too difficult if you know
your fundamentals and your basics,
which is the goal of this video.
It's just to tell you what,
what's the whole idea of it.
And if you want to learn more
about the mathematics behind
it, refer to my other videos.
On introduction to stoichiometry, limiting
reagents, gas stoichiometry, and solution
stoichiometry, and probably many more
that are going to come as time passes.
So, the whole idea with this is
when we're looking at stoichiometry
is, can you read a recipe?
And essentially, like, if you cook
at home or make anything or even,
heck, if you just read the back of a
box to microwave something, you have
essentially used some kind of recipe.
Even if you've just ordered food, right,
to actually prepare all those things,
how are they putting all together?
If you ever made something, you're
following instructions and it takes so
many ingredients to put that together.
That's where we're going to be relating to
this, is something as simple as cooking.
Let's take a look.
Say I want to make a simple cheeseburger.
Well, if you were to make a burger at
home, or to cook anything, you'd probably
follow a recipe, you'd probably Google
it, look it up in the Food Network
or some kind of recipe, and you'd
see exactly how to make it and see if
you have those ingredients at home.
Or maybe you'd just listen from the heart
and just mix things together, but you're
still following some kind of recipe.
Meaning that there's a specific
ratio between all those ingredients
to make the thing you want, right?
If you don't follow them, you're going
to, you're going to start trying to
make like something like bread and
you're going to end up with a cake.
They're going to be
completely different things.
So if I want to make a burger,
well, how would I do it?
Well, my secret recipe is up
here, so don't tell anybody else.
As simple as just taking a hamburger
patty with a slice of cheese and
two buns, And you got a burger.
Now, if we were to write this out,
let's say if we want to show it
more like a chemical equation,
well, we could do that, right?
So right here, I have my two buns and
they're mixing with my piece of cheese.
and mix them in a patty and they
exist within a specific ratio, right?
We see two buns with one slice of
cheese and then one patty mixing
those together to make one burger.
Now, if I were to ask you something
really simple about this recipe, how
many burgers can I make with 13 buns?
So you look in, you look in your
pantry, you see the only have 13 buns.
And let me say you have as many as
much hamburger meat and cheese in
the fridge as you possibly want.
You have them in excess, meaning
there's a ton of them available.
How many burgers can you make?
And well, you're probably like
thinking like, well, I can
make six and a half, right?
So 13 divided by two for
the buns, six and a half.
And you were able to think of that without
really doing any type of fancy math or
anything you've learned in chemistry.
So you'd be like, well, what's
the whole point of stoichiometry?
Well, that's the whole idea is
you're looking at relationships.
So from those 13 buns, we can
simply just say that we have.
We can make six and a
half burgers from that.
Now, how could we show that in
terms of actual stoichiometry?
Let's take a look at what this is.
So when you're looking at this recipe,
essentially all this is, is showing it.
Can you show it with dimensional analysis?
Stoichiometry is only, is
just dimensional analysis.
It's unit conversions.
Since the very beginning of my
channel and all these videos that I
show, give to all, all my students,
I've been telling everybody since
day one, it's just unit conversions.
That's all chemistry truly is.
Can you cancel your units?
So if we want to do the same problem,
right, where we said we were starting
with 13 buns, so let's say if I take
My buns from all the way up here and
I'm to copy them down Can we actually
show this like a math problem?
Can you cancel it?
How did you get to six and a
half by doing that in your head?
Well, you simply saw that okay based
on the recipe above that there were
two buns equivalent to every One
burger that were up there, right?
So you saw that there was
a relationship, right?
So for every burger, we have two
buns that are there, and we can
essentially show that, hey, there
is a relationship with that, right?
For every one divided by two, and we can
see, well, what happens to that is that
your units end up canceling as a result.
So you got 13 divided by two
made six and a half burgers.
So you did that dimensional
analysis in your head, right?
So, and this is the same idea
as what stoichiometry is about.
Can you essentially cancel
something as simple out?
as food or burgers or whatever
it is that you're trying to see.
So let's try to look at this slightly
different but with the same example.
So instead of looking at it just like
pictures, what if we make our recipe
look like a chemical reaction where I
all of a sudden replace all the pictures
and goofy little things where I have
two buns with one piece of cheese
with one patty is equal to a burger.
You can show that the exact same
way, and we can illustrate that
our units are going to cancel out.
Now the important, most important
part about this is that is this middle
component here in the middle, which
showed that there was a relationship
found within our chemical equation, right?
Two buns were equivalent to one burger,
meaning that essentially with any
chemical equation, you can use the
coefficients to relate different terms.
So for every two buns,
you make one burger.
For every two buns, you need
one piece of cheese, right?
For every two buns, you need one patty.
There are all these different little
relationships that can be found with them.
Now, even though we said that, oh,
one burger is equivalent to two buns,
you could say all kinds of recip
different, uh, relationships that
are of the same, um, essentially the
same, uh, depth between them, right?
So one to two.
I could also say one dozen burgers is
equivalent to two dozen buns, right?
It's the same one to two relationship.
Same thing if I want to use something
that's a little bit more common when it
comes to looking at chemistry, right?
One mole of burgers, which would be a
ton of patties, or a ton of burgers,
is equivalent to two moles of buns.
There's the same one to two relationship.
So we can use this in terms of balanced
chemical equations to show a relationship.
Let's take a look at
an example using this.
The whole idea of stoichiometry
is you're trying to put chemical
equations to work, right?
Can you put a balanced chemical
equation and show what the
mole to mole relationship is?
So this is going to use,
uh, our chemical equations.
We can use molar mass, molarity,
ideal gas law, all these other
concepts can come into play.
Because the goal is always the mole.
If you can get the moles, you can then
use the balanced chemical equation to
predict, to be able to figure out how much
are you going to make, how much do you
need to make all these different recipes.
It's something very important.
So let's say if I take this.
Unbalanced chemical equation.
Can I put this to work?
Well, first things first is when we
want to balance this, first tip that
I always give is even out the odds.
Meaning that if you notice on the right
hand side, we have three hydrogens, on the
left you have two, so they're not even.
So if I were to even it out, right, where
now I have six hydrogens on the right,
and six hydrogens on the left, now our
problem, if you notice, the nitrogen's
balanced, everything is balanced.
So what can we do from this?
Well, we can show different relationships
here between all these coefficients that
are in front of all these numbers, whether
it's one with NH3, or H2, or even the one
here for nitrogen, which is equivalent to
a one, we can define these, which is what
makes chemical equations very powerful.
So, for example, if I want to
say, start with nitrogen, I could
say that one mole in nitrogen is
equivalent to, uh, two moles of NH3.
I could also say that one mole of
nitrogen is equivalent or can be converted
to three moles of hydrogen, right?
So those are equivalent as well.
And just to kind of make it a
little easier, right, we can show
the color coding here that we had
earlier just to be able to follow
so we can see what's equivalent.
Now is that everything
that can be equivalent?
Well, we can also do the same thing.
When it came to, with, uh, hydrogen
as well, three moles of hydrogen
is equivalent to two moles of NH3.
There are multiple relationships that
are hidden within the chemical equation.
And the thing of all these is
because they're conversion factors,
you can flip them and use them to
convert from one unit to another.
So let's say you start
with some with grams.
You can use the molar mass
to convert that to moles.
And then you can use the chemical
equation to go one step farther.
It's powerful, knowing
how to do stoichiometry.
It's one of the most important
things that we do in chemistry,
is to be able to predict.
For our last example, let's say
if we start with the exact same
type of problem we had earlier.
Which was when we did our
hamburger example, we had so
many number of buns available.
What if we do it with moles
in the chemical equation?
Well, if I have 17 moles of ammonium,
right, so which is our product here
at the very end, and I ask you, how
many moles of nitrogen and hydrogen
did you start with in this problem?
How could we do it?
Well, the first thing is when we have
a relationship here, we can define
all of the different mole fractions.
Now, do you have to write them
every single one of them down?
The answer is, the short answer is no.
You have to pick which
ones you need to use.
So, in this problem, what we can,
what we are starting with is that we
know that we have 17 moles of NH3,
and the first thing is that it asks
you to do is to go to the nitrogen.
Okay.
So what is our relationship
between ammonia and nitrogen?
And one thing that we can
see is, well, for two, every
two moles of ammonia, right?
So if I kind of write that down
here, two moles of NH3, I am going
to need one mole of nitrogen in
order to make ammonia, right?
So there's a two to one relationship,
which is coming from those chemical
coefficients that we showed earlier.
We're using this relationship over here.
Now when we do that, right, so 17
divided by 2, What are you gonna have?
Well, that we're gonna have eight
and a half moles of nitrogen
is what our answer is gonna be.
We can write that down.
So eight and a half moles of N2, right?
So that gives us an idea of
exactly how many moles that we're
gonna have for our first problem.
Now, what about for hydrogen?
Let's do the same thing.
So let's move this down and we're once
again gonna be starting with 17 moles of
of NH3 and we're going to use the chemical
equation for what our relationship
between ammonia and hydrogen are.
Well, if you remember, for every
2 moles of NH3, there is going to
be 3 moles of hydrogen, alright?
And that's given us another
relationship that's here.
What we can do is we do 17 times 3 divided
by 2, and that's going to tell you that,
hey, you, you have, you started with 25.
5 moles of H2, so you can
convert this to different units.
Thanks.
Now, if you need to figure out the mass,
or let's say how many liters of gas
there are, you could do even follow up
steps, which I do in my other videos.
So this is the idea.
So that's the final concept of
stoichiometry, is can you read a chemical
recipe, because all it does is takes a
balanced chemical equation and relates
that to moles, it follows the dimensional
analysis idea as a unit conversion,
so can you convert, can you balance.
And if you need that help, look at my
other videos to help you with that.
Go look through the homepage
that everything's labeled by
playlist to help you further.
Okay.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope you have a wonderful day.
And this was your first time here.
Please hit that like and subscribe button.
And if you are confused, comment below and
I can help guide you to the right place
and help you with the resources you need.
Okay.
Thank you.
And bye bye.